Guide to the Robert K. Greenleaf Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Robert K. Greenleaf Papers
1927-1991
RG 287
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(19 boxes)
The collection documents Greenleaf's professional life, including as founder of the Servant Leadership movement and of the Greenleaf Center for Servant Leadership, which was first known as the Center for Applied Ethics.
Greenleaf, Robert K.
Biographical / Historical
Greenleaf was born in 1904 in Terre Haute, Indiana. He attended Rose Polytechnic (an engineering school) in Terre Haute for several years, then transferred to Carleton College in Minnesota. He graduated as a math major in 1926 and took a job with AT and T (telephone company). During his 38-year career with the company he served as Director of Management Development, originator of the world's first corporate assessment center, promotion of the first females and blacks to non-menial positions, a program to expose up-and-coming leaders to the humanities, even bringing in famous theologians and psychologists to speak about the wider implications of corporate decisions.
Greenleaf retired in 1964 and began his second career as a writer, consultant, and teacher. His seminal essay "The Servant as Leader" was published in 1970. In 1976, Paulist Press published a book of his essays titled "Servant Leadership." He died in 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School Collection, 2017
Scope and Contents
The collection includes autobiographical material, correspondence, subject files, writings, and memorabilia.
Arrangement
Series I. Journal and Autobiographical Material
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Subject Files
Series IV. Unpublished Literary Manuscripts
Series V. Publications
Series VI. Memorabilia
Leadership; Greenleaf, Robert K.
- Journal and Autobiographical Material, Series I
  - Journal, 1940–1943 (Box 1)
  - Dreams (3 notebooks & 2 folders), circa 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Notes from work with Jungian analysts Ira Progoff and Martha Jaeger
  - Miscellaneous notes on autobiography project, No date (Box 1)
  - [Hole in the hedge philosophy], 1954 (Box 1)
  - [Narrative of life and work through 1920s] - 2 drafts, No date (Box 1)
  - My work with AT&T - 2 drafts, No date (Box 1)
  - My work in education - draft, No date (Box 1)
  - My work with churches - draft, No date (Box 1)
  - My work with foundations - 2 drafts, No date (Box 1)
  - My work in India - draft, No date (Box 1)
  - Age 40-60: What I did with those years - draft, 1986 March 15 (Box 1)
  - [Narrative of life and work after age 60] - draft, No date (Box 1)
  - The institution as servant, reflections on experience - draft, No date (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Series II
  See more correspondence in the Subject Files.
  - Of Greenleaf
    - Letters, 1931–1978 (Box 2)
    - Letters, 1979–1981 (Box 3)
    - Letters, 1982–1984 (Box 4)
    - Letters, 1984–1985 (Box 5)
    - Letters, 1986–1988 (Box 6)
  - Not to or from Greenleaf
    - Correspondence concerning Greenleaf and the Greenleaf Center, 1982–1993 (Box 6)
- Subject Files, Series III
  For a more detailed listing of contents of subject files see the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Articles and clippings (Box 6)
    Including on "Coercion, Manipulation & Persuasion", "Gandhi, Nehru, India", "Leadership, Trustee", "Servant Ideas"
  - Carleton College (3 folders), 1934–1967 (Box 7)
  - Catholic (3 folders), 1978–1984 (Box 7)
  - Center for Applied Studies (6 folders), 1968–1985 (Box 7)
  - Cheswick Center (2 folders), 1975–1976 (Box 7)
  - Church of the Saviour (4 folders), 1975–1984 (Box 7)
  - Council of Foundations, 1973–1985 (Box 7)
  - Deurinck (3 folders), 1973–1985 (Box 8)
  - Fable (3 folders), 1983–1987 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation (2 folders), 1963–1970 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation - India (8 folders), 1963–1971 (Box 8)
  - Frost (Robert) ( 2 folders), 1961–1972 (Box 8)
  - Gandhi - John Woolman, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Harvard Divinity School, 1965–1971 (Box 9)
  - Gerald Heard (3 folders), 1955–1966 (Box 9)
  - Abraham Heschel, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Hill Foundation (2 folders), 1973–1975 (Box 9)
  - Humanities Project (2 folders), 1958–1976 (Box 9)
  - Inner City Church (2 folders), 1984 (Box 9)
  - Intuition Seminar - MIT ( 2 folders), 1962–1963 (Box 9)
  - Leadership - College Programs, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Lilly Endowment Fund (3 folders), 1972–1984 (Box 9)
  - Lilly Endowment Fund (5 folders), 1972–1984 (Box 10)
  - Loveless, 1975–1979 (Box 10)
  - Mailing lists (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Management Objectives Program, 1963–1964 (Box 10)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (2 folders), 1971–1977 (Box 10)
  - Mead Corporation, 1970–1971 (Box 10)
  - Mentoring (3 folders), 1983–1985 (Box 10)
  - Nashville (Indiana) Conference (2 folders), 1977 (Box 10)
  - North Carolina Visit, 1975–1976 (Box 10)
  - Northwest Area Foundation, 1977–1978 (Box 10)
  - Ohio Bell Telephone (3 folders), 1929–1931 (Box 10)
  - Ohio Bell Telephone (1 folder), 1929–1931 (Box 11)
  - Ohio Bell Telephone - Henry Meade, 1942 (Box 11)
  - Persuasion, 1978 (Box 11)
  - Post Office, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Quakers - Tom Brown (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Quakers - Memoirs (3 folders), 1937–1969 (Box 11)
  - Quakers - Mission to the Quakers (3 folders), 1937–1986 (Box 11)
  - Quakers - Pendle Hill, 1976–1979 (Box 11)
  - Quakers - Pendle Hill Conference (2 folders), 1976 (Box 11)
  - References to Greenleaf's work (3 folders), 1975–1987 (Box 11)
  - Seminaries (4 folders), 1979–1985 (Box 11)
  - The Servant as A Person (Jefferson House) (6 folders), 1975–1977 (Box 12)
  - Servant Leadership, 1977 (Box 12)
  - Servant: Retrospect and Prospect, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Bennett Sims (3 folders), 1983–1985 (Box 12)
  - Sisters of Mercy (3 folders), 1976–1983 (Box 12)
  - Strength (2 folders), circa 1978 (Box 12)
  - Theology of Institutions (2 folders), 1978–1980 (Box 12)
  - Trustees as Servants (Revised) (2 folders), 1975 (Box 13)
  - Unitarians, 1975–1977 (Box 13)
  - Wainwright House (2 folders), 1956–1978 (Box 13)
  - Washington Amherst Conference, 1972 (Box 13)
  - E.B. White (2 folders), 1934–1987 (Box 13)
  - Whittier College, 1972 (Box 13)
  - William Wolf, 1960–1971 (Box 13)
- Unpublished Literary Manuscripts, Series IV
  For a full list of titles see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Essays
    - Undated, arranged by title
      - Untitled, "Abortion - "Notes on community in the Late Twentieth Century" (Box 13)
      - "Notes on Institute of Chairing" - "You Need To Be Human" (Box 14)
    - Arranged chronologically
      - Essays, 1937–1987 (Box 14)
  - Meditations
    - untitled, incomplete notes, No date (Box 15)
    - Church as Servant, No date (Box 15)
    - Manager, Administrator, Statesman, No date (Box 15)
    - An Opportunity for a Foundation Concern in the Field of Leadership, No date (Box 15)
    - Reflections on Experience, No date (Box 15)
    - A Sense of History, No date (Box 15)
    - What are you called to do? A sense of Vocation, No date (Box 15)
- Publications, Series V
  For a full list of publications by Greenleaf see the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Articles by Greenleaf, 1951–1980 (Box 15)
  - Articles by Greenleaf, 1981–1990 (Box 16)
  - Anonymous articles attributed to Greenleaf, 1936–1974 (Box 16)
  - Collaborations, 1927 (Box 16)
  - Collaborations, 1932–1995 (Box 16a)
  - Writings of others, 1932-1995, no date (Box 16a)
- Memorabilia, Series VI
  - Notebooks, 1964–1968 (Box 17)
  - Date books, 1963–1986 (Box 17)
  - Address book, No date (Box 17)
  - International certificates of vaccination and personal health history: Robert K. and Esther H. Greenleaf, 1962–1971 (Box 17)
  - Passports: Robert K. and Esther H. Greenleaf, 1930–1979 (Box 17)
  - Bookmark: "The Marks of a Yokefellow" (Box 17)
  - Undated and childhood memorabilia, 1914-1924, no date (Box 18)
    Includes letter of Greenleaf to his mother, report cards
  - Memorabilia from college years, 1923-1926, no date (Box 18)
    Includes Carleton College handbook and directories, letters regarding summer employment and the Men's Glee Club
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1968, no date (Box 18)
    Includes documents re marriage license and certificate, poem to commemorate retirement from Dartmouth program
  - Material re honorary degree awarded by Carleton College, 1969 (Box 18)
  - Photographs, No date (Box 18)
  - Obituaries and memorials of Robert K. Greenleaf, 1990–1991 (Box 18)
    Including by Ed Ouelette, Alfonso Narvaez, and memorial service program at Bangor Theological Seminary